Okay, so all those ideals that shaped
and sustained the American Revolution
had massive effects on its society as
well. And not just American society, but
places in Europe and the Caribbean as
well. And I reckon we ought to talk
about it. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay. Now, as I mentioned in a previous
video, one of the main factors that
secured an American victory in the
Revolutionary War was the widespread
adoption of powerful ideas. And ideas,
as we know, have consequences, sometimes
altogether unforeseen. For example, our
boy Thomas Jefferson wrote in the
Declaration of Independence that all men
are created equal and that such a truth
was so far beyond argument that it was
just self-evident. And to call something
self-evident means that the only
criterion for believing it is that you
have a pulse and at least a minimally
operative thinkythinky zone. And so
Americans really latched on to this idea
that all people were created equal. But
then both during and after the
revolution, people began looking around
and growing question marks over their
head because certain social structures
seem to contradict this truth. And I'm
going to give you two examples. Oh, and
by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, then check the link in the
description. Okay. First, revolutionary
ideals increased awareness of the
inequalities of the system of slavery.
Now, many delegates in the Continental
Congress were themselves planters and
slave owners, including Thomas
Jefferson. And many of them were not
ignorant of the contradiction between
championing liberty for all men while
simultaneously enslaving a portion of
them. So, why didn't they just go ahead
and ban slavery right there? Well, it's
complicated, but one particular event
made them a little twitchy. namely the
issuing of Dunore's proclamation during
the war. So when the Revolutionary War
spread to Virginia, the loyalist
Governor Lord Dunore issued a
proclamation which said that any
indentured servant or enslaved black
person who fought on behalf of the
British would soon afterward earn their
freedom. And as it turned out, many
enslaved blacks did take Dunore up on
that offer and fought on the British
side. And while Dunore's proclamation
raised the possibility for freedom in
the minds of black Americans, it got
southern colonial leaders real sweaty
because it stoked their fears of
enslaved rebellion. And it further made
them sweaty on account of it challenged
the rigid social hierarchy on which all
of their wealth and status was built. In
fact, Jefferson actually included an
indictment against slavery in the
Declaration of Independence. But the
rest of the Congress shut that right
down because they fear that such an
inclusion might alienate the southern
colonies. Therefore, after the war, when
new state constitutions were being
written, most of them permitted slavery
to remain. Only Vermont's constitution
abolished slavery and Pennsylvania's
mandated a gradual emancipation of
enslaved people. But as you might
imagine, when black people of all
stripes heard that all men are created
equal, they assumed that such an ideal
meant that all men, including black
people, were equal, and therefore
slavery had no place in the New
Republic. But since these elite planters
relied heavily on slavery in order to
maintain their status and wealth, the
institution remained entrenched in the
United States, serving as a significant
contradiction to one of the ideals
closest to the heart of American
identity. As a result, during the war,
thousands of enslaved blacks in the
south fled north and joined the growing
societies of free blacks that existed,
especially in busy port cities.
Regardless, this glaring contradiction
of revolutionary ideals emboldened some
groups to call for the abolition of
slavery, most of them residing in the
north, where slavery was less important
to their economic well-being. And I'd
like to tell you that their efforts were
fruitful, but you know, it took like
another century before slavery was
abolished. Okay. Now, the second way
revolutionary ideals affected society
was through calls for greater political
democracy. So, the revolution itself was
both articulated and led by a handful of
elite white men. And their desire to be
free of the rigid hierarchy of British
power did not prepare them for the fact
that their ideas would filter down
through society and cause common folks
to want to rid themselves of the social
hierarchy present in the United States.
You know, a lot of people are thinking
they just exchanged the tyranny of a
British hierarchy for an American
hierarchy. Well, that's just because
they're dumb and poor.
Oh, yeah. I hear it now. But, uh, no,
somebody's still got to be on top. And
so the flurry of elections that
populated government positions became
debates on the merits of expanding
democracy by recognizing the right to
vote for more and more people. As it
was, most state constitutions had
property requirements for voting and
that led to calls for the removal of
such strictures. However, this
particular application of revolutionary
ideals just like the abolishment of
slavery would require many years to
fulfill. Okay, now let's turn the corner
and talk about how revolutionary ideals
affected women in the United States.
Now, I need to tell you upfront that
women played a very significant role in
securing the victory in the American
Revolution. And I know that when you
think about the revolution, you most
likely think of companies of stanky men
hurling their bodies into battle to
secure the win. And yeah, that's true.
But it is not the whole story. For
example, farm wives took up the plow and
ran the farms while their husbands
fought in the war. Other women became
camp followers, which means they
traveled with the Continental Army
serving as nurses or attended to the
needs of the soldiers. Still, other
women actually disguised themselves as
men and fought right alongside the other
stanky men on the battlefield. Anyway,
for their vital role in securing
independence, women certainly believe
that the equality for which the
revolution was fought included them as
well. And that's not a bad assumption.
In fact, even before the revolution
began, we can see women already calling
out for their rights. For example,
Abigail Adams wrote to her husband John
Adams while he was at the Second
Continental Congress just a couple
months before Jefferson finished the
Declaration of Independence. And she
articulated a clear expectation that
women be included in the expansive
liberty of the new nation when she said,
"Remember the ladies." If per chance the
delegates did not remember the ladies
Abigail wrote, "We are determined to
fment a rebellion." Abigail Adams, you
diva. However, despite all of this,
after the revolution, equality patently
did not extend to women, most notably
the franchise or the right to vote.
However, within women's subordinated
social role, men seem to understand how
vital they were to the flourishing of a
republican government. In light of that,
Benjamin Rush advanced the idea of the
Republican motherhood. And basically the
idea here was that the most important
way a woman could contribute to and
participate in a republican society was
to thoroughly educate their sons about
the notions of liberty and government.
And that meant that in general women
were praised for fulfilling their
domestic role. But recognizing them as
political equals to men well you know
huh no. I mean as men saw it if women's
autonomy was recognized then that would
undermine the role of men as head of the
household which would infringe on their
liberty. After all, they reasoned
someone needed to make the sandwiches,
and the right to vote would just
distract too much from that womanly
duty. Even so, while the notion of the
Republican motherhood kept women from
active political participation, it did
expand their access to education, which
was a welcome opportunity for many of
them. Even so, political equality for
women would have to wait until the 20th
century. Okay. Now, in the previous two
points, I was emphasizing how
revolutionary ideals highlighted social
inequalities, but then only had
minuscule effects. But here's where I
tell you that across the Atlantic world,
the American Revolution and the ideals
on which it was based had some pretty
major effects. Mainly in the form of
other revolutions based on similar
principles. And I'm in the mood to give
you three examples. First, the American
Revolution inspired the French
Revolution. If you'll recall, many
French soldiers participated in the
American Revolution and returned home
inflamed with the ideals of democracy.
Therefore, when the absolutist turd
Louis V 16th attempted to tighten his
control over France in order to pay his
own enormous war debts, the people of
France rebelled, overthrew the
government, and established a republic.
And enlightenment principles also
undergurted the main document of this
revolution, namely the declaration of
the rights of man and citizen, which
asserted the principles of natural
rights and popular sovereignty. However,
the revolutionaries in France went a
step further than the Americans and
championed social equality as well. And
as it turned out, that was more than a
little stanky to some Americans who had
successfully kept their own social
hierarchy intact before and after their
revolution. Second, these revolutionary
ideals inspired the Haitian Revolution.
So Haiti was France's most profitable
colony by far, and a small minority of
white authorities ruled over a much
larger majority of enslaved black
laborers whose work in Hades various
plantations was altogether degrading and
brutal. But when news of the French
Revolution reached the island, the
ideals of freedom and self-ruule proved
exceedingly attractive to the enslaved
population and stirred up a desire to
overthrow colonial authorities and
dismantle the system of slavery. And so
under the leadership of Tusant Luvatur,
the enslaved Haitians revolted and
eventually defeated the French,
establishing the first black government
in the Western Hemisphere. And finally,
third, these revolutionary ideals led to
various revolutions in Latin America. In
that region, Spanish and Portuguese
colonies throughout Central and South
America were similarly influenced by
enlightenment ideas and began to resent
the increasing control their imperial
parents were exerting upon them. And so
long story short, military leaders like
Simone Bolivar appealed to colonial
subjects across racial lines with
enlightenment ideals, including appeals
for popular sovereignty and the right to
self-ruule among the various Spanish
colonies. And so through a series of
long and protracted wars, one Latin
American colony after another won its
independence, and many of them formed
republican governments in its wake.
Okay, click here to keep watching my
other unit 3 videos, and click here to
grab my video note guides, which are
going to help you get all the contents
of this course firmly crammed into your
brain folders. I appreciate you coming
around and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm Laur.